foreign
it's June 15 2023 we are here in lecture
two of Chris Fields course physics as
information processing so thank you
Chris looking forward to the lecture
oh thank you Daniel
um and yes welcome to this session
uh this section is titled why quantum
physics
and if you will recall from the first
session
we reviewed the history of physics and
and some of the history of mathematics
and computer science
or I'll
the end from the end of the 19th century
through to the beginning of the 21st
Century
and discuss the the slow development
from classical thermodynamics
of quantum information Theory
and uh specifically characterizing
Quantum information Theory
as a new kind of physics
that
describes systems that are exchanging
finite amounts of discreetly encoded
information
across some intervening boundary and
so we use this very conventional
graphical notation
of two agents or physical systems
Alice and Bob A and B
that are exchanging energy and
information
across some boundary and I always use a
blue ellipse like this to indicate the
boundary that separates Alice from Bob
and this new approach to
physics is entirely topological it's not
geometric
so it doesn't assume a particular
background space time
so it doesn't assume that Alice and Bob
are spatially separated
and so this this makes it a very
different kind of theory from classical
information Theory
in that the channel uh that separates
Alice from Bob this boundary
is a boundary in state space it's not a
boundary in some geometric embedding
space and in particular it's not a
boundary or a channel that's embedded in
a three-dimensional space that separates
Alice from Bob
that's what we talked about last time
and today what I want to discuss is how
quantum
theory in particular
makes this idea of physics is a theory
of communication simple than obvious and
quantum theory of course has a terrible
reputation
uh of being abstruse and mathematically
incredibly complicated and
counter-intuitive and difficult to
understand
and this is one quotation among many
of from leading physicists pointing out
that that quantum mechanics is just
difficult
and uh as as you probably know there's
an entire
philosophical industry of
interpretations of quantum theory
that try to make sense of its ontology
and
so what I don't want to do today is try
to introduce quantum mechanics
uh we're not doing uh any of this
some of you will recognize this as the
table of contents the first part of the
table of contents of the famous textbook
by Landau and lift sheds
oh but if you've studied quantum theory
in undergraduate or graduate school
you've probably dealt with a textbook
structured much like this one and you've
probably been introduced to quantum
mechanics as it was traditionally
conceived as essentially a mechanical
Theory a theory of motion
uh with wave functions and and particle
representations and on and on and on
so we're not going to try to do that
this uh what we're going to do instead
is take a completely
information theoretic approach
uh and we're going to characterize
um information transfer in a Quantum
theoretic way without any assumptions
about mechanics or space-time or any of
that
so instead of this
we're going to ask a simple question
uh a simple by a simple question I mean
a question with just a yes no answer or
a binary answer so let's use up or down
as our example question
and to ask this question we need three
things
first we need an action we need a way of
asking it
uh for example making a sound or writing
something down
um second we need to a thing that we can
ask the question of
uh we need an environment or a friend or
the rest of the world or an experimental
apparatus
or some system or other that we're going
to act on to ask this question
and the third thing that we need to to
ask this question is a shared language
and it's the shared language that's
often neglected in in
models based in physics
um and I think the importance of the
shared language was became clear and
classical information Theory and it's
it's become clear again of course in
Quantum information Theory but this has
only happened over the last few decades
so what I want to do today is to
construct in a step-by-step fashion a
formal representation of these three
things that we need
to ask a simple question
and what we'll find is that that formal
representation is in fact quantum theory
so it's quantum theory that provides us
with a formal representation of asking
these simple binary questions and of
course if you can ask a binary question
you can ask any finite number of binary
questions so you can construct and
arbitrarily complex finite decision tree
that ends up formulating
an arbitrary an arbitrarily complex but
still finite question
so this really is a general model of
communicative interactions between
agents
so let's go about this and and talk
first about the action of asking a
question and so the first thing I want
you to do is is actually say out loud
up or down
actually
ask a question
and then note two things about what just
happened
uh the first thing to note is that it
took some time to do that that that
action actually we required to find that
amount of time
um
a couple of seconds not very long
but it's not zero it it always takes
time to ask a question
and the second thing to note is that it
took energy
to to actually say up or down
it requires a little bit of exertion
to ask a question
so let's put those two together
and Define a word we're going to define
the word action
to mean some energy that's spent in some
time
so asking a question is an action
and it qualifies as an action because it
requires spending some energy in some
finite amount of time
and so we can write this as action
equals energy times time or I'll
sometimes use the abbreviation E times t
um
and
action is is always required when when
there's some interaction
or two-way action
between systems so whenever we talk
about physical interaction we're always
talking about two systems doing
something to each other
that requires both energy and time
so let's define another concept a
concept of a minimum action needed to
ask a question and specifically a
question with a binary answer
and we'll just pick a symbol to stand
for that minimum action and the symbol
we'll use because it's conventional as h
and it turns out that this h
is Planck's constant the number that
Planck came up with
when he was trying to solve the black
body problem back in 1900 that we talked
about last time
and recall that was the problem of
characterizing the spectrum of radiation
emitted by some physical system that was
hot
how much energy comes out as a function
of temperature
and if you assume that the spectrum of
energy coming out is continuous you get
predictions that are wrong
and plank got predictions that were
correct
by assuming that that Spectrum was
discrete and that that this h
uh represented the minimum amount of
energy that could be emitted in a
particular time so it represented the
minimum energy times time or action
so let's look at an example of that
and here's an example that may be
familiar it's the example of your own
visual system
so in the retinal
the cells of your retinas
uh there are many many molecules that
are rhodopsins of one variety or other
that respond to different wavelengths of
visible light
and they have some efficiency for
capturing light
and let's just assume that they're
optimally efficient that there is
efficient as they could possibly be
and that means that they require the
minimum amount of energy
to change shape which is what they do
when they're impacted by light to
capture the the energy and hence the
information that's available in the
light
and the minimum energy to do anything
that records one bit of information so
yes or no up or down
uh is 0.7 so log 2
um
of of Boltzmann's constant times the
temperature
and again we saw this last time uh this
is from roughly 1875.
and was then built into classical
information Theory
by Shannon and then by landauer uh in
the mid 20th century
so what we're doing is is assuming that
since rhodopson's optimally efficient
all it requires is this amount of energy
to change shape
and it's known experimentally that
rhodopsin takes about 200 femtoseconds
to change shape so that's 200 times 10
to the minus 15 seconds so it's a very
very fast reaction chemical reaction
so we can just calculate what the action
is
and at 37 degrees Centigrade so human
body temperature
KT is about 4.3 times 10 to the minus 21
Joule my joules just the standard unit
of energy
and so we can multiply everything
together
um
KT times 0.7 times this response time of
200 femtoseconds
of
multiplied together gives you an action
of about 6 times 10 to the minus 34
Joule seconds
and if you're familiar with quantum
mechanics you'll instantly recognize
that number because it's very close to
the value of Planck's constant uh which
is 6.6 times 10 to the minus 34 Joule
seconds so this says that rhodopsin is
very near to Optimal
um the the best it would be able to do
would be Planck's constant that's the
minimum action that can be undertaken
um so rhodopsin is clearly doing very
well it can't be as efficient as we're
assuming it to be
uh but it's pretty efficient
so this number Planck's constant is and
this idea of a minimum action is not
something we just pulled out of the air
it's something that one can observe when
you're looking at what real biological
systems in particular do in other
physical systems too
so let's think about the the second
component of of this
project of asking a question and that's
the thing to be asked
and we want to ask a very simple
question we want to have a theory of
asking very simple questions
so let's define the simplest thing that
we can ask a binary question too
and let's say this is the thing that we
can ask a binary question of using just
this minimum action h
so we're going to ask for the minimal
thing that it's possible physically to
ask a question of
and this thing needs a name so let's
call it a qubit and that word is a
contraction or Quantum bit
and we can draw it like this a little
sphere with an arrow through it Ah
that's called a block sphere
and we use this symbol q and that
notation with the bar and the angle
bracket
uh
is called a bra notation and it
originates with Dirac so it's a
traditional way of writing inner
products actually in quantum theory
[Music]
um
to indicate the state of Q
so we'll we'll this this thing called a
qubit uh only responds to Binary
questions so it clearly can have only
two states the state that answers yes
and the state that answers no
and conventionally we we draw the arrow
going up if the answer is yes and the
arrow going down if the answer is no
and so those are the two states that the
qubit can be in when it's answered a
question
so now let's draw a picture for the act
of asking a question of Q in the state q
and let's draw it like this
uh this curviero is the action of asking
the question and getting the answer back
and we're asking it of this minimum
system the qubit
and let's call this this entire Act of H
and right at H acting on Q by this
expression HQ
so again we're developing the the
notation of quantum theory which uh all
of you who
know the theory already will find
familiar
so the third thing that we have to to
build into this picture and into the
theory
is the shared language
so we have to know uh what we mean by up
or down if we're going to ask the
question up or down
and we have to I'll have some
representation of of
what it means for the qubit to
distinguish up or down
so let's say that to us
oh
up and down mean this little diagram
with an arrow that's labeled up on one
end and down on the other end so we're
defining up and down in a very simple
way as just opposites we don't know
anything else about them except that
they're opposites
so this is a stripped down one bit
question we could have called them one
and minus one we could have called them
A and B we could have called them
anything
uh we're just indicating that up and
down are two opposing Concepts
and so this object that we've used to
make this definition
of the relationship between our two
words up and down
is called a reference frame
uh it's it's a
a physical object
that encodes a concept or a meaning
and if you think about using language
using English for example you can
understand me speaking in English
uh because your brain has the right
sorts of neural circuits to allow you to
understand English and produce English
uh using your your hand in your mouth
and those neural circuits are reference
frames in your brain uh for
understanding and producing English and
they encode the relationships between
different words
so you all know about chat GPT you can
think of all of the weights on
uh all of the 10 to the
19th or however many parameters there
are in gpd4
as a reference frame
that describes the relationships between
words and phrases in English and many
other languages
so this idea of a reference frame
is an instance of of Land hours
principle which is is often summarized
as saying that information is physical
what that means is that information
always has to have some encoding
and that encoding that object
can always be thought of as a reference
frame
so let's put all this stuff together
what we have now is a reference frame
that defines the difference between up
and down we have an action that we've
labeled h
and the action acts on this object of
the qubit
uh which is in some state
and what we've drawn here now is an
experiment
and you can think of the incoming part
of the arrow that goes from the
reference frame to the qubit
as a preparation of the qubit so you can
think of it as I'm doing something to
the qubit to put it in a particular
State like up
because that's the state I want it to be
in
and I can think of this returning part
of the arrow
as a measurement of the state that the
qubit is actually in
so if the qubit's actually in this state
with Europe pointing up
uh then I'm going to get back the answer
up when I act on the qubit to measure
its state
so now we can recognize this this action
h
as
the hamiltonian operator in quantum
theory
which always takes some time
which we represent by an interval DT
to act on some State and in particular
this binary state q so this is this
whole picture depicts the action of a
very simple hamiltonian operator
um and again I want to emphasize that
we've just defined the qubit as the
simplest thing that we can ask a binary
question of
so how does this H work
uh we can use h
to prepare this qubit in one of two
states which we're going to label one
and minus one
of the state one
uh corresponds to the up Direction
and the State minus 1 corresponds to the
down Direction
and
doing this to Q so preparing Q in one of
these two states takes energy
and we know how much uh boltzmann told
us back in 1875 that the minimum energy
to reduce the the entropy of the
universe by one bit
is log 2 of KT we saw that earlier when
we were thinking about rhodopsin so we
can say that acting with h always
requires some number times KT where that
number is bigger than the log of 2. and
remember the log of 2 is just in there
to get units of bits of binary questions
uh as opposed to units of gnats which
are questions that have
e answers where e is the exponential
base the natural exponential base but we
want to use units of bits so we have to
always have this factor of log 2.
so this lets us write H in a particular
way we can take out this this energetic
term
that vaultzmann tells us we have to
include uh beta times KT
and what's left over is is in a sense
the pure representation of the action
stripping out the energy requirement
and we're going to call that M because m
is the standard
symbol to use in quantum theory for a
measurement operator
and M is is now dimensionless H uh has
units of energy KT
is in energy
and M has no units at all so it's h
without the energy
so now we can ask what is this operator
M that we've defined as the the simplest
possible
action on a qubit but abstracting away
the amount of energy that we have to use
to act on the qubit
well what M does is just encode a bit or
decode a bit
so we can use this operator M to say uh
I want Q to have the value 1 I want it
to be up so I can sort of reach out with
my operator M and grab q and turn it so
that its arrow is pointing up
and that's what the the operation that's
called preparation in physics it's what
it means to prepare an experimental
apparatus for example you you actually
grab hold of the apparatus and you twist
some knobs and flick some switches to
prepare it to be in some state
and you can use M to measure a state
that isn't known so I can
use M to grab a hold of Q and look at it
and determine whether it's in state 1 or
-1
and I can represent these as just a
cycle that starts with measuring and
then prepares or that starts with
preparing and then measuring
and if I represent it that way
uh what I see is is m
having a value which is either the value
I want to encode or the value that I
have measured and Q
and M acts on that value and Q to
produce a particular state of Q to put Q
in a particular state or to realize that
Q is in that state
and so m is actually an identity
acting on some value and Q so it Maps
one and Q to 1 and Q and it Maps minus 1
and Q two minus 1 and Q
if you do the whole cycle of preparation
and then measurement and that makes
sense it's actually an axiom in some
formulations of quantum theory
that if I measure the state of some
object
what I'm doing is also preparing it in
that state so if I immediately measure
it again I'll see the same value
and that makes sense physically if I you
know put my coffee cup on the table and
then I look for it it's likely going to
be on the table unless something else
intervenes
well what does this mean it means that
we can do a little bit of algebra
um
it means that we can write this original
expression
of acting on cue with our hamiltonian in
this somewhat more explicit form of
using the energy beta KT
and our operator M on Q
and what I get out of that is the energy
beta KT multiplied by Q
so HQ equals EQ
that's the Schrodinger equation
so that's one of the central equations
of quantum theory what it says is that
this operator h
is the total energy operator on a system
its eigenvalues are the total energies
of the system
and we can now see where that energy is
coming from in this very very simple
strip down
kind of of representation of an action
the energy is the thermodynamic energy
that has to be spent to determine one
binary
outcome up or down
now if you're familiar with quantum
mechanics uh you will have seen
exponentiated operators uh like the the
next line here of algebra
this operator P which is time dependent
and which is the exponential of H
uh multiplied by i t over H bar
is called the propagator it's the
unitary operator in quantum theory the
operator that conserves probability or
conserves information
and so
using the representation of H
as beta KT we can see that that this
operator p is just e to the minus beta m
uh if we recall the wick rotation from
the first session
of this strange equivalence of i t over
H bar with 1 over KT that wasn't
discovered until 50 years after the
invention of quantum theory
um and that's still a very debated uh
thing I mean people worry about what
this what this equation really means
but one thing that it means in this
setting where H has this particularly
simple form
is that the propagator is now just
the exponential of a number multiplied
by this very simple strip down operator
that
um
encodes a bit or decodes a bit
but we know something about the
exponential propagator just by looking
at its form if you're again familiar
with these sorts of exponential
operators you know that they're wave
equations
and we can make sense of that using the
diagram up above what m is doing is just
performing a cycle
uh it's just mapping 1 and Q back to
itself
or minus 1 and Q back to itself so we
can think of of M
as just taking this object and flipping
it back around until it's uh
until it gets itself again
and that kind of cycle can always be
turned into a wave equation
and e to the I over H Bar times h t is a
canonical form of a wave equation where
the the horizontal axis here on the wave
is time or if you look at the little
cycle that I've drawn as a circle with
an arrow it's it's the time of the thing
spinning around like this which
is exactly the same thing as a wave
traveling through time
so that tells us something very
important
it tells us that that this equivalent
expression e to the minus beta m is also
a wave equation
so it tells us that this operator m
has built into it some sense of time
um it's the sense of time of this
prepare measure cycle
and that's implicit in m
right we've used the wick rotation to
get rid of the the kind of what what
I'll end up calling the external time T
the objective time t
and we'll see in July uh
where this internal time comes from
uh in terms of the wick rotation
but
we can say now that it's an agent
specific time it's an internal time
reference frame
that's built into the our idea of this
system Alice that can act on the world
and it represents the time that's
required to ask this question
okay Chris uh can I ask a question at
this point yes uh so on this slide uh
with the operator
um I'm curious that's how can the agent
deploy in the operator m
tell the difference or break the
Symmetry between preparation and
measurement
or are they just completely dual
pictures
um
yeah they're completely dual so the
agent the agent never breaks the
Symmetry the agent can't actually
distinguish the act of preparing from
the act of measuring
every preparation is a measurement and
every measurement is a preparation right
that's that's in fact what this Axiom of
of
measuring a state
leaves the particle in the measured
State means right
so yeah mathematically they're duals
thank you
okay so let's let's now use this theory
that we've developed to describe the
interaction between Alice and Bob
and let's think of this situation in
which Alice prepares a qubit
that Bob then measures
and then Bob prepares the very same
qubit and that Alice measures it
so Alice acts with her hamiltonian
operator which will label h a
and Bob acts with his hamiltonian
operator that we label HB
and let's say that Alice prepares the
qubit as in-state up
and uh Bob can then measure the qubit in
state up and say oh the qubit is now up
and if Bob then prepares the Cuban State
down
uh Alice can measure the qubit in state
down and say oh the qubit switch from
the up that I prepared to down so Bob
must have prepared it is down
so what's happened here
uh Alice and Bob have actually shared a
bit flip
right Alice said uh up and and Bob said
down so
and Alice heard him say down
so they've they've shared this idea of
change
by interacting with each other
now this works as long as they mean the
same thing by up and down
so we've implicitly assumed in talking
about them communicating that they both
have this reference frame
that distinguishes up from down
and this is actually a completely
General model
of what I'll call a noiseless one qubit
channel now what does that mean it's
noiseless because there's nothing else
in the picture
right there's nothing else in the
picture that can jiggle the qubit when
else and Bob aren't looking Alice and
Bob are the only systems we're talking
about
and they share this qubit and there's
nothing else in the picture so there's
no kind of third party or environment or
heat bath or anything like that that's
going to mess with the qubit
and disrupt their interaction so that's
a noiseless channel and it's a one qubit
channel because they just have one qubit
that they're interacting with and
they're alternately
preparing and measuring at state
now clearly if if they can interact
using one qubit they can interact using
any finite number of qubits
so here's a picture of an in qubit
Channel
that uh Alice and Bob which here I've
labeled A and B because I took this
figure from a paper
are sharing
and uh
Alice and Bob both have n operators one
for each of the N qubits that they share
and they just do this prepare and
measurement cycle on all in qubits so
you can think of Alice preparing the in
qubits Bob measuring the in qubits and
then Bob preparing an ALICE measuring
and that allows them to to exchange
in-bit messages and we can make n as
large as we want and so they can
exchange messages of arbitrary
complexity
and if they share the meaning of up and
down then they can exchange these
messages with no noise
so they can communicate
and we now have our theory of two
communicating agents
that are that are sharing
arbitrary uh finite information
now I've labeled uh q1 through qn in
this picture uh a holographic screen
and in fact that's exactly what it is
I'll recall from Session One this slide
illustrating the holographic principle
um
Shannon made this point that a bit of
information is an answer to a yes no
question
and
so we can
write down a number of possible States
we can write down an entropy
um and
the limiting case of that entropy is the
entropy of a black hole the densest
possible uh
encoding of information
in space
or on a boundary
and this holographic principle allows us
to see any boundary as we discuss in
session one as an encoding of bits
so the previous boundary of these in
qubits we can think of as a holographic
screen
now
why is that important
um
it's important because it allows us to
use this idea of holography
and this idea of
fixed encoding of a message or a fixed
encoding of an observable entropy
at some density
that was developed in cosmology
to talk about arbitrary Quantum
communication channels so we can import
a whole bunch of theory that was done
someplace else
into Quantum information Theory and see
that it works perfectly because it
describes exactly the same situation
what does this tell us
philosophically
it tells us that Alice and Bob can learn
about each other
at most in bits per communication cycle
so the maximal amount of information
that they can get from an observation is
the in bits that the other one wrote on
the screen
so this tells us something very
important that when an agent is looking
at their environment which is this other
agent Bob
the amount of information that can be
extracted from the environment is
actually proportional to the size in
bits of the boundary
and the holographic principle just makes
that size finite in space
and I said early on that there's no
embedding space time in this theory that
Alice and Bob are not thought of as
separated in space
but as soon as we use the holographic
principle we can think of the boundary
between them as having a spatial
coordinate even though they don't have a
spatial coordinate
so uh we'll get back to this point in
September when we talk about theories of
emergent SpaceTime but all of these
theories of emergent space-time come
back to this idea that boundaries can
have spatial extent even though the
systems that they separate don't have
any natural spatial description or
natural spatial degrees of freedom
okay
so
now let's recall another picture from
Session One
uh
we talked a little bit about
feynman's theory of scattering
and the the origin of Feynman diagrams
and the idea that if Alice prepares some
system in some initial state
and then measures the state later
if we want to calculate what the new
state is
we have to take into account all of the
possible paths
that join the initial state that Alice
prepared to the final state that Ellis
measured
so what does that mean
I mean here effectively if we think of
suppose I'm Alice and the boundary is my
screen
I'm talking to the screen
and then later on I'm going to measure
the screen
and between my preparation actions and
my measurement actions a bunch of stuff
happens on the other side of the screen
and if I want to predict what's going to
happen on the other side of the screen
I've got to take into account every
possible thing that could happen
and uh I have to give some weight to
those possible things that could happen
and quantum theory in fact tells you how
to assign those weights to things that
could happen in order to make a
measurement given some theory of the
mechanism that makes things happen
but the fact that all of the paths have
to be counted as what unitary Evolution
means this in this this Evolution that
preserves information that doesn't take
any away it doesn't add any it just
represents it in different ways so if
you look at the screen
and imagine that Alice is interacting
with her boundary
and then she's interacting with her
boundary again it looks just like the
previous screen
and the way they read arrows are what's
happening inside Bob
the wavy red arrows are a representation
of what's going on inside Bob as he
measures
his side of the screen and then prepares
his side of the screen
so what Feynman is representing here
is just the action of the environment or
the action of the system
uh while Alice isn't looking
between Alice's preparation stage and
her measurement stage while Bob is is
doing his measurement in preparation
so this diagram is actually completely
symmetrical we could have drawn an arrow
where the the wavy red things are and
drawn wavy red things where we've talked
about Alice and we'd have the same
picture just from Bob's point of view
we can also think of this of course as
Alice communicating with her first
future self by writing a memory record
someplace in the world and then coming
back and reading it
and if Alice writes a memory on the
world
and then comes back later on and reads
it she actually has to take into account
some theory of all of the things the
world might have done to her memory
while she wasn't looking
um so this picture of feynman's actually
tells us a lot about memory
and when we think about organisms
running around in the world uh doing
things
like we do all the time
um we tend to think of memories as
things that are are persistent and
unchanging and all of that but we know
that that's not true
we know that memory is degrade in
various ways
uh we know that uh adversarial third
parties can come and and change what
we've done so that they fool us into
thinking that we've remembered something
that we haven't
and so on and so forth
that whole picture of memory
is actually encoded in in this picture
that Feynman Drew
in the late 50s to represent scattering
of particles
so what we've done here is started with
this simple idea of asking questions
and we've actually constructed a fair
amount of quantum theory we constructed
the Schrodinger equation we constructed
the unitary propagator we constructed
the idea of a reference frame
which we'll talk about intensely next
time in July
so we can sum this up by saying that
quantum theory simply is a theory of
communicating agents
and that quantum mechanics
of the theory that Feynman was
complaining about
in that earlier slide
the quantum mechanics generates this
problem that seems intractable of how to
understand measurement
because the theory is in fact about
measurement it's not about mechanical
motion at all
so Quantum Theory actually tells us
nothing about ontology
and this is why the interpretations of
quantum theory the the many worlds
interpretation where you have all these
branching universes
uh and so forth are not really science
they're philosophy their attempts to
understand an ontology
of
that's generated by a theory that
doesn't talk about ontology it talks
about communication between agents
but we've left something very important
out we've left out a consideration of
what happens when Alice and Bob don't
mean the same thing by up and down
and we've left out the famous phenomenon
of entanglement
uh
spooky action at a distance as Einstein
called it and it turns out these things
that we've left out are very very
closely related
and we're going to see why
in July and I'm going to give you a
brief preview now
so what happens when Alice and Bob
actually mean different things by up and
down what if their reference frames
aren't aligned
well the first thing to note is that
nothing in the theory says they have to
be aligned
so we have to consider the possibility
that they're not
and in fact both Alice and Bob have to
have what's called free choice of
reference frame when Alice prepares her
her instrument she has to be able to
prepare it any way she wants to in order
to do an experiment
and uh when Bob makes up a sentence to
tell Alice uh he has to be able to
choose any language he wants to use
he's a he's a free agent in this way
and if they don't have that freedom it
turns out they're entangled so reference
frame non-alignment and entanglement are
very very closely coupled
now misalignment of reference frames is
what produces superpositions of outcomes
so if Alice makes her measurements with
her up and down arrow arranged
vertically for example
but Bob prepares his qubit with his up
and down
Arrow
arranged at 90 degrees to Alice's Alice
is not going to have any idea what Bob
did
I mean she can't see distinctions in the
left right direction she can only see
distinctions in the up and down
Direction
so all she can do is flip a coin
if she wants to know what uh Bob
prepared it's 50 percent likely he
prepared up for her what she calls one
and it's fifty percent likely that he
prepared what's down for her she can't
tell
oh now if Bob
if Bob's reference frame is pointing at
about 45 degrees so up for him means 45
degrees off of Alice's up
then she can sort of tell what he did
if if he's pointing 45 degrees from Up
then uh she's probably going to measure
up
and if he's putting 45 degrees from town
she's probably going to measure down
so her outcomes are 75 percent for one
and 25 percent for minus one if he
prepares uh at this 45 degree angle
so we can write this in a particular way
we can say that
the value that Alice gets acting with
her M on a qubit that Bob prepared
is some number times what she measures
is up plus some other number plus times
what she measures as minus one
where those numbers the squares of those
numbers add to one
so why do they have to add to one well
they add to one because of the
Pythagorean theorem
oh
one is the distance the total distance
between the two outcomes
and
um
a squared plus b squared are the other
two sides of that triangle so
um
another way to think of it is that
the metric distance
of
[Music]
impossibility space is one
and a squared and B squared are just the
euclidean distance components again
euclidean distance is based on the
Pythagorean theorem
so this is the born rule in quantum
theory
uh it's the rule that tells us what
happens when we're trying to measure a
superposition
and it tells us where these
superpositions come from uh
we have a mismatch in in reference
frames between two agents that are
communicating
so
if we go back to the free energy
principle which is what uh this whole
active inference class is about
and we formulated in quantum theory we
get a very simple idea of what the free
energy principle is
the fep and quantum theory just says
that interacting systems are going to
behave in a way that aligns their
reference frames
and that makes their communication as
good as it can be
uh but since aligning reference frames
perfectly
leads to entanglement
of the free energy principle drives
systems asymptotically toward
entanglement
well the principle of unitarity
says that all systems will approach
entanglement asymptotically
so we can see the fep is actually a
classical statement of the principle of
unitarity
and what we'll see in the next session
is why this is the case why active
inference when we think of a Quantum
mechanically is a way of talking about
the principle of unitarity which is the
deepest Axiom of quantum theory
and we'll also see that this question of
alignment becomes more and more complex
as the complexity of the messages of the
CIS that the systems are trying to
communicate to each other increases
and the message complexity correlates
with system complexity
so that aligning complicated systems is
very hard
although aligning very simple systems is
fairly easy if you think about
uh what's the what's the simplest
possible
theory in science it's particle physics
because you're dealing with these very
simple things that interact in extremely
simple ways
and the really difficult parts of
science are things like sociology
where you're dealing with uh incredibly
complicated systems like humans that
interact in incredibly complicated ways
and all we have are very vague kind of
folk theories of how that works
but we know from that example that
aligning complex systems is extremely
difficult
um
it's what humans don't get along very
well
so the second session uh well the second
discussion section which Andrew will be
leading is on Saturday the first of July
a couple of weeks from now
the third lecture session will be on
July 13th
and uh I hope you all will contribute to
the interactive question and answer
session on the web
and uh show up for the discussion on
Saturday the 1st of July and join us
again in July for the discussion of
quantum reference frames and reference
Frame Alignment
so thank you very much
thank you Chris
all right thank you all again please
check out the chorus syllabus
ask questions through the site and
see you at the discussion see you next
time
thank you bye